alright guys in the last video we went
ahead and added our JavaScript to add
and remove our classes dynamically for
the menu we also created the cool ex
effect here when we click our menu so
now what I want to do is work on the
overlay okay and we have our our nav
links right here and nav items but
obviously we don't want these to show by
default so we have quite a bit of CSS to
write I should say sass so let's go into
our menu dot s CSS I'm gonna close up
some of this stuff we don't need these
and let's just make this bigger alright
so let's go down we'll go all the way
down outside of everything and we want
to create our menu overlay and we're
gonna grab the class of menu and let's
position it to be fixed oops position to
be fixed and we'll say from the top we
want 0 and then we want the width of it
to be 100% and the opacity and you don't
have to add opacity if you don't want it
to be see-through I like the see-through
effect and what I mean is if we go here
you can kind of see that see the page
behind it you know if you don't want to
add opacity then don't add this if you
want it to be just you know gray without
the background but I like the effect of
seeing behind it so we're gonna set that
to 0.9 and we want this to by default we
want the visibility to be hidden right
because we don't want the links and or
anything to show by default so let's say
visibility and set that to hidden so if
I save now we can no longer see it okay
now when we hit the button then we want
remember the show class is going to be
applied so we want to add for the show
attached to the menu so ampersand
thought show then we want to set the
visibility to visible so let's save that
and now if I click this now it's visit
bull okay if I click it again it goes
away so let's take care of like the
branding and the nav and stuff like that
now since the the class name is menu
branding what we could do is instead of
and we're gonna go inside here we're
gonna nest
instead of doing dot menu - branding we
could actually say ampersand and then
just add - branding whoops that
shouldn't be a zero should be a -
branding so that's going to represent
this whatever this is and then it's
gonna add on to it - branding so we
don't even have to do like class menu
branding just a neat little trick now I
also want this styling to go for the
menu nav okay so we have a class of menu
- nav so I'm gonna put a comma here and
we're gonna say ampersand - nav alright
so that'll be menu branding and menu nav
so we want this to be displayed as flex
okay so we want to display flex and
let's do let's make it into a column so
if we say flex - flow we want to set it
to a column which means going up and
down as opposed to right and left and we
also want it to wrap okay so we'll save
that and if we click this we're not
going to see any difference yet but we
want to align the items to this Center
so let's say aligned items to Center we
also wanted to we want to justify the
content to the center as well so we want
to align both vertically and
horizontally to the center and then we
want both to float left and let's set
the width to 50% because we want each
each side to take up 50% of the width
and for the height we want the height to
be the whole thing so we're going to use
a hundred VH okay so viewport Heights
where they said like a hundred slices so
it's gonna take up the whole thing and
what we're talking about is both of
these sides this styling has has to do
with both of these so flex is gonna make
it into a column so that's gonna make
like these links go this way instead of
this way align items will Center it will
Center it this way and then justify that
way so that it's in the center we're
folding both to the left with this 50%
so we want to split it in half and both
of them have the height of a hundred
viewport Heights we also want to put an
overflow hidden because we never want to
have any scroll bars so let's say
overflow and set that to hidden all
right so now let's go back to our
project and try it out so if we click
this you see the nav is now down here
it's in the middle of its 50% side and
there's no portrait there's no image
because we haven't added that yet but it
will we will have that we'll also have
the background for each side this is
just the styling that I wanted to apply
to both the branding side and the nav
side so now we need to do each separate
one so within the menu okay but outside
of this here we want to do
ampersand - nav okay so just the nav
side and we're going to just margin
we're going to zero out the margin and
padding and let's add a background now
the background I want it to be I want it
to be the primary color but I want to
darken it a little bit so I'm gonna use
darken just part of sass and we want to
say primary - color and let's set 5 okay
so if we save that and we click and now
you can see we have the dark gray and
since we set the opacity of the menu to
0.9 we can see through it okay so the
next thing I want to do is get rid of
the list the icons I'm sorry not the
icons the bullet points here so it's an
list - style
style and we'll set that to none okay I
get rid of those now notice how when
this shows up when we click this it just
pops in and I don't want that I want it
to slide in from the top so we're gonna
use something called translate 3d which
is a value for transform for the
transform property so as you can see
here if transform translate 3d takes in
positioning attributes or parameters and
you can see each one of these it just
kind of moves it around because of these
values that's the zero position so what
I want to do is on the nav I want it to
not show until the show class is applied
and then we want to basically change the
translate 3d parameters so let me show
you what I mean we're gonna say
transform and then say translate
actually translate 3d we want and we're
gonna start off at zero 100% zero and
that's going to just kind of take it off
the page it's gonna put it it's going to
put it up here and then we want it to
transition down so we're gonna also
include our mixin of ease out so let's
say include ease out now when the show
show class is applied to the nav so we
want to go down here we want to say
amperes amp and then dot show so when
that's applied we want it to slide in
from top and we can do that by changing
the translate3d parameters so translate
i'm not translate transform and then
translate 3d and we want to take the
values now and just zero them all out so
now if I click this actually I want that
to come in from the top since I want it
to come in from the top we need to set
this to negative 100
because what 100% is doing is its
pushing it down it's pushing it down if
we do negative 100% it should be up
so it's do- 100 and now it comes in from
the top the other side we want to come
in from the bottom so we'll do a hundred
percent there but yeah that's that's
good
now before I work on like how these
links look and stuff like that and how
they fly in from the side I want to
handle the branding side so let's go
still within the menu you still want to
be within the menu but you want to go
outside of the nav here so to be right
here and let's say branding side so
we'll do an % - branding to target the
menu - branding class and let's set the
background so this background I just
want set to the primary color because
remember the other one we darkened so
this one will just have just a regular
primary color you'll still be able to
see through it because the menu class
has the opacity and we also want to set
the ease out here so let's say include
he's out and we're gonna do the same
thing with the translate3d
so let's grab this and actually put that
right here except this time remember we
wanted to come in from the top so it's
this middle value is gonna be 100% we're
pushing it a hundred percent up and then
we on show we want it to come down so
we're gonna do the same thing we'll grab
this and show put that in here except
actually no this is the same exact thing
we just wanted to come back to its place
so it'll slide in from bottom let's try
it let's save and now if I click that
there we go alright so let's handle the
portrait because right now it's
completely empty remember we have a div
with the class of portrait inside the
menu branding so we won't you still want
to be within the branding and this is
where that bracket colorizer comes in
handy so you can tell where you're at
see the different colors here so we're
gonna go right here and let's say dot
portrait and we're gonna set the width
of this to 250 pixels we're going to set
the height to 250 pixels and then the
background we're gonna set that to a URL
you could put this in a variable for
easier access but I think it's fine so
dot dot slash into the image folder and
then we want portrait dot jpg okay I
also want it to be circular so we're
going to give it a border radius of 50%
which will make it into a circle and
then I'm gonna add a border to it which
will be Solid 3 pixels and we want it to
be the secondary color so let's put the
variable of secondary - color okay let's
try it out we'll save and now there we
go get the little portrait
so now let's handle the nav items so I'm
gonna go say right outside here still
within the menu and say dot nav - item
so let's see we're gonna do the same
thing with the translate3d we basically
want it to be off the screen until we
get the show so let's say transform
translate3d now we're not going up and
down we're going left and right so we're
dealing with the first parameter and I'm
gonna say 600 pixels okay so basically
we're moving it off the screen to the
right 600 pixels to start with and we
want to include our ease out
and then when the show class comes we
can actually just copy this so when the
show class comes we want to slide in
from right like that all right so yeah
let's save that and see what happens
when we click all right now snow tiss
how it is sliding in from the right but
it's it's not right the whole entire
thing is coming in so what we're
actually going to do here is create a
delay okay so for each item when it
slides in we're gonna create a delay so
we're gonna we're actually going to use
a sass for loop here I'm gonna go down
to the bottom and let's just put a
comment in here and we'll say delay
delay each nav item slide by 0.1 seconds
so we want to set we want to do a for
loop so at 4 and we basically want to
just create like if you do a for loop in
Java Script you'll use like X or Y or X
or I or something like that as an
iterator so I'm going to just use money
sign X and we're gonna say from 1
through 4 because we have 4 links okay
are 4 items so it's like it's like in
JavaScript doing 4 and then saying like
let's I or in this case let X equal 0
and then saying as long as I is as long
as I is less than 4 and then I plus plus
it's kind of like doing that in
JavaScript or or any language really any
for loop so for each one we want to take
the nav item so now I've - item and we
want to take the nth child so : nth
child remember we can select each one
so and child.and in here like if we look
at the links the the first one would be
this one second third fourth but we want
to loop through and we want a variable
in here now I can't just put money sign
X that'll give us an error we have to
actually wrap this in a number sign and
then curly braces it's kind of like a
template literal in Java in es6 so if we
do that for each one for each end child
for basically for each link here we want
to set a transition delay so we'll say
transition - delay and we want to set
the delay to whatever the variable is so
X which is going to you know start at
one go through four and then we want to
multiply it by 0.1 seconds okay we don't
want them all to be delayed by 0.1
seconds because it'll still all come in
at the same time we want like 1 times
this 2 times this 3 times this so that
each one comes in separately okay
hopefully that makes sense let's save
this and then let's try it out and there
we go so they kind of just fly in
awesome alright so the next thing I want
to do is style the links because right
now they're way too small we need you
know a little bit of spacing I also want
them to be all capitalized or uppercase
so let's let's style those I'm gonna go
right here actually let's see where do I
want to go let's go right here so we're
still within the menu and we're gonna do
our nav links so dot nav - link and
let's see what how do we want to style
these let's let's display them as
in-line blocks in line
block and position them relative and
let's let's increase the font size so
we'll say font size and I'm just going
to use 30 pixels and then let's do a
text transform to make them all
uppercase and let's set some padding on
the top and bottom so 15 top and bottom
and I'll actually we'll just do one rim
I'll use REM units and then 0 on the
left and right font weight font weight
I'm gonna do 300 color we're gonna for
now just set it to white and then let's
also make sure that there's no I know
there's no underline but just let's make
sure so text decoration we want that set
to none and then let's let's add the
transition as well so we want to include
ease in our ease out so let's save that
there we go so if we click come in from
the side good so on hover I want them to
be the secondary color also the current
page that we're on should be the second
and secondary color so the current page
is going to be attached to the nav item
if we look at the index.html you'll see
we add current did I even do it no I
didn't
so this first nav item since this is the
index.html page I'm going to add the
class of current and save and now we'll
go back here and for a nav item let's go
down and say ampersand dot current and
we want the link so we're gonna say
inside that the link is what we want to
actually color so let's see we want to
say color which will be secondary color
all right so let's save that and check
it out okay so now the home is yellow
and again we also want hover which is
going to go on nav link so I can
actually just I'll just put it in here
so within nav link we're gonna say
ampersand : hover and we want the color
to be the secondary color so now when I
hover we get that yellow alright guys so
I think I think that's it for the
overlay as far as this now we do have
the responsive version to do because if
we look at the responsiveness so you can
see this looks like crap and then the
overlay really looks like crap so we
want to kind of we want to change this
up so we're gonna do a couple things but
before we do that let's just make a
quick commit because we did do the
overlay for for basically for desktops
so I'm gonna go to my other terminal
here and let's just say git add all and
let's do git commit and whoops let's say
we'll just do menu overlay alright so
we'll go back to our other terminal here
and now let's create some mix-ins for
our media queries I like to put them
inside of mix-ins when I use SAS so in
our config file let's go down to the
very bottom and we'll say media query
mix-ins so to do that we'll say add mix
in and we're gonna have small medium
large and extra large so let's do mobile
not mobile we'll say media SM that'll be
the name of our mixin and here we want
to put the actual media query so at
media and we're gonna do screen and and
then the size so we're gonna say max
width of 500 pixels okay so this is how
you create a
media query and what this means is that
any CSS we put in inside of here will
only apply if the screen is 500 pixels
or less okay so 500 pixels is I don't
know it's like around here or something
so anything we put in here would be in
for that size now since this is a mixin
we're not gonna actually put our CSS in
here I want to be able to use this mix
in elsewhere so all we have to do is in
here is put content so anything we put
inside this mix in in another file we
can just we can just add this mix in and
it'll get automatically put inside here
where we put content so we're going to
just grab this and we need three more so
this one here is gonna be let's say
medium action any comments it's obvious
so media media MD and this is going to
be four screens that are 768 and under
okay so 768 and under and then for large
so we'll do LG for large we want to do a
range so I'm gonna add let's see let's
add right here a set of parentheses and
we'll say min width so for screens that
have a min width of 769 pixels and I use
69 because it's one pixel after this so
if it's 769 if it's between that and a
max width of let's say one one seven
zero okay so if it's between that whoops
I should have an end here as well let me
just close this up so if it's between
this and this then this these styles
will apply okay so basically if it's
between like 768 which I'd estimate like
right here and then 1 170 which would
probably be like I don't know right here
or something like that that would be the
media large now media extra large we
want to
to another range so let's say men
actually know we don't want to do a
range here we're just gonna say men with
I want to same end with of one pixel
above this which is one one seven one
okay so anything above that is gonna be
this this media query so if you want
something to only display or whatever if
you want some CSS and only huge screens
like this then you would you would use
this media query alright so those are
the media queries now we need a place to
actually put our responsive CSS so I'm
going to create a new file inside s CSS
called mobile dot s CSS I'm sorry
underscore mobile it's a partial and
before I forget let's just go to main s
CSS and import mobile like that alright
and I'm also going to just restart down
here if I'm going to ctrl C and then NPM
run sass again just in case any time I
create a new file I reset that so in our
mobile s CSS we want to use the mix-ins
we just created so this one let's do
extra-large first we'll go kind of top
to bottom so this will be for wide
screens so to use the mixin we use
include and we want media Excel okay so
that will be for wide screens and let's
just grab this so we want three more so
the second one here is gonna be for
let's say desktops and laptops and this
is gonna be our large and then this one
here is gonna be for tablets I'll say
tablets and maybe some small laptops so
this will be medium MD and then this one
here is for let's say smartphones
so media SM okay so now anytime you want
CSS for a specific screen size you just
put it within one of these media queries
so I'm gonna save this and let's let's
start with just the before we do the
overlay let's go to get this figure it
out so I want this to be displayed I
want everything like in the middle and
in the the main area here on medium
screens and smaller so let's go into the
MD and let's add main and let's say
align
- items we want to align these Center I
also want to text a line text a line
when I keep doing that 0
text-align:center and save and let's see
what are we getting an error down here
no mixin named media Excel wait a minute
let's go into our config oh it has a
capital L we only want this that this to
be capital I don't save that and there
we go so now everything's in the middle
good let's see so I also want the
heading I'm going to change the line
height because see how much space is in
between here so inside the main tag
right here let's do a dot LG - heading
because that's inside the main tag and
we're gonna set the line height to 1 and
let's set margin - bottom - 1 REM and
save and there we go so that looks good
let's see let's make it really small so
like right here this is where it changes
to MD so MD large MD large I also want
let's see let's let's actually move this
down a bit so for the small inside the
small I'm gonna say main let's just do
main ID home h1 and I'm gonna say from
margin top I want it to be 10 of
viewport heights okay and save so just
just so when if this is shorter I always
want it to be 10 viewport heights I
think that's all I need to do for the
home page responsiveness now we want to
deal with the overlay because I mean
that that actually looks okay but once
it gets really small it just it doesn't
so we won't want to fix that so all the
stuff that we're going to do is going to
be within that the tablets and small
laptops because this affects not only
the tablet size but anything below that
as well so first thing we'll do is add
let's go below the main make sure you're
not within the main and let's say you l
dot menu - nav as well as the div dot
menu - branding so this will be for both
and right now they're floated to the
left so they're side-by-side we don't
want that so we're gonna say float none
we also don't want a width of 50 percent
for each we want a hundred percent
because we want if we look at the final
project here and we go to medium you'll
see that now there are a hundred percent
each because they're not floated so
let's say with 100 percent let's see
we're also gonna set a min height of
zero and then we want to do for the show
okay so when the show like when they
come when the overlay comes in we don't
want them to come in from the top and
bottom we want them to come in from the
left and right so we need to change the
transform and translate ID
properties so let's go still within here
we're gonna say ampersand oh and then
say transform translate3d
and we're gonna say zero zero zero so
that's when when it shows now when it
doesn't show we need to change those
values with values as well so let's
start with the nav the menu nav so I'm
going to go below let's see we want to
go right here just make sure you're
still within the media query so still
within media MD and let's do dot menu -
nav and we're gonna set the height of
the menu navin t5 viewport Heights now
if we look at the final project you can
see this is the menu now if it's 75
viewport Heights so remember a hundred
slices it takes up 75 this will take up
25 so let's do height 75 let's do our
transform translate3d
now instead of coming in from the top
and bottom where we would use the middle
parameter now we're coming in from the
left and right so we want to use the
first parameter so this is going to be
negative 100% and then zero zero okay
that's its resting place and then on the
show it'll come into view but it'll come
in from the side and then finally I just
want to change the font size let's say
font size to 24 pixels alright so if we
if we look at it now it's gonna its it's
messed up right because we need to
finish but for now that's what it looks
like for the branding for the menu
branding let's go right below the menu
nav and let's do that
so menu branding
and we want to set that height to 25
viewport Heights okay so then the nav is
75 this the branding is 25 and then we
need our transform translate 3d and this
is going to come in from the other side
so a hundred percent the other one was
negative 100 because we want that to
come in from the left this one's coming
in from the right so we want a hundred
percent okay so if we go ahead and check
this out it looks like that which is
we're almost there but the image is too
big so in your images file you'll notice
a portrait dot jpg and a portrait small
dot jpg so we need to change the
portrait to that smaller image so within
menu branding let's add the portrait
class so let's say portraits and set the
background to URL and we want to set
that to dot dot / IMG / portrait
underscore small dot jpg and then just
set the width to 150 pixels instead of
instead of 250 and then also the height
set that to 150 pixels and save and
there we go all right so now if we make
this really small it still looks good
everything still looks good awesome so
we now have the the men used on the
overlay the homepage and the
responsiveness in our config file we can
change colors we can change the if we
want the image shown stuff like that the
opacity just to test the colors let's
say I don't know let's choose like like
a dark green and then for the secondary
we'll choose a below this is going to be
really ugly but let's save and there we
go
okay now we're gonna create a mix in
we'll do this in the next video we're
going to create a mix in that we'll make
it so that when it's on a light
background for instance if I make the
primary color white and save you'll see
it doesn't it doesn't look good because
the Texas is white so we can't read it
so we want to mix and that will
determine what the color should be of
the font based on the background color
so what we will do that will also start
on the other pages so let's just put
this back to dark gray and yellow and
then let's just make our commit real
quick again you guys don't have to do
this but I'm gonna say get add all and
get commit actually we just need AB so
get commit and what do we do we we
basically made our site responsive so
let's just say added media queries and
made an you overlay responsive whatever
it doesn't really matter alright so in
the next video like I said we'll get to
the detect changing the text and then
we'll start to create our other pages as
well