all right in the last video we created
our boat page and we added the
responsiveness we use the grid grid
template areas now we're going to create
our not a contact our work page so let's
create in the dist folder a file called
work dot HTML and we're gonna copy let's
copy the about page actually so we'll
grab all everything that's that's index
let's grab everything that's in about
and let's paste it into work okay and
we'll just kind of we'll close this up
and let's go up to the top let's change
the title to we'll call it we'll just
save you my work and let's change the
current class from the about to work so
right here okay and then we'll go down
here let's change the LG heading to my
and then secondary will be work let's
also change the ID here to work and
let's see for this for the for the
little subheading let's say check out
some of my projects alright and then
let's see we're gonna use the grid here
as well so I'm gonna this this div with
the class of about info I'm going to
change this to projects and then just
get rid of everything in it okay so this
div ends here so everything inside
projects let's get rid of all right we
want the footer the same that's that's
fine so in the projects we're gonna have
a class of item we're gonna have a bunch
of these but I'm going to create the
first one first so item inside here will
have just an a tag that doesn't go
anywhere so I'm just going to put just
put a number sign in an exclamation and
this will be the image for the project
so it's going to be image it's going to
have actually it's not going to have a
class till the source will go to image
slash remember we have that projects
folder and then we have project
jpg and then for the alt for the alt I'm
just going to put in project doesn't
matter so inside the item we have the
link around the image now under that
link with the image inside of it we want
to have an a tag with the class of BTN -
light so we're going to create some
button styles
okay so BTN light like that doesn't
matter where it goes and then inside
this BTN light let's put an icon so I'm
going to use an icon with the class of
FAS and the class of FA - I like that
and then next to it we're going to say
project okay so that's the link for the
project now I'm going to copy this a tag
here put another one below it I'm going
to change it to button dark and then
we're going to change this to fa -
github because we want this to be the
github icon and then we'll change the
text also to get up okay so if we save
this and we go to my work it's gonna
look horrible okay the image is full
size but don't worry about it for now
for now we just want to copy the div
with the class of image this whole thing
here and let's see we have how many do
we have actually so we have one two
three four five of these so let's do
five so that's one let's do two three
four and five alright now we want to
change a couple things actually we just
want to really change the image of each
one so with project one second one will
be project two dot jpg we can keep this
stuff that's fine
project three four and five okay so if
we save that we're just gonna have three
huge images with this text here but
that's that's pretty much it for as far
as the HTML go so we can actually close
that up and close up about and let's
open up
Maine dot scss and we want to start
working on the the projects area so down
below
let's go above the footer I like leaving
the footer at the bottom
let's go below the about CSS that we did
and let's say work slash projects and we
have a class of projects we're gonna
display this as a grid so display grid I
want to I want to shrink the images down
real quick before we do anything else so
all the images that are embedded inside
projects we want to set the width to
100% of its container so let's save that
that'll shrink it down alright now for
the grid we want to we want it to be by
default three F three fractional x'
across okay so three images or items so
let's say grid - template columns and
let's set this to just like we did
before we'll set it to repeat three
times one fractional like that and save
okay now we want a little bit of a gap
as well so let's say grid gap and let's
do 20 pixels like that what else do we
want to do here let's let's let's add a
border to the image so right here will
say border and the border for the images
I just want to be white they don't have
to be a special color I want the hover
to actually be the secondary color but
by default let's make them white and
solid okay like that and then let's put
let's do the hover of the images so
inside here will do ampersand colon
hover
and we want the I'm gonna actually make
the opacity of the image I will say
opacity let's make it 0.5 when we hover
over it and then let's make the border -
color so we just want to affect the
color secondary color and then let's do
the transition as well so we can simply
include the ease out and now if we save
when we hover over the images you can
see it fades the opacity fades in we get
the transition we get the yellow border
and so on alright um what else do we
want to do here obviously we want to do
these buttons but actually I think the
grid gap I used I used REM units
originally so if you want to change that
let's do 0 0.7 Ram like that there we go
alright so let's do the the buttons now
I'm not gonna embed the button light and
the button doc into into the projects
because I want to be able if we wanted
to use these buttons anywhere else I
want to be able to do that not just
within projects so we'll go down below
here and let's say button styles okay
you could even create a button dot s CSS
if you want you could do like how
bootstrap does in every little element
create a separate SAS file but I don't
really like doing that so we're going to
use a little bit of inheritance here so
I'm gonna create I'm gonna do a class of
BTN now notice we didn't act we don't
have a class of BTN attached to anything
but I want these the button light and
the button dark to have some similar
styles wait a minute why isn't that
github showing let me just check that
real quick I think I FA - github what
should that should be showing I class F
a github the heck let me just
double-check this oh it's F a B so when
you use social media icons it's not FAS
its F a B so for the first class so we
just want to change those
alright there we go alright so back back
to where we were so for the BTN style
here this is like we're gonna we're
gonna create some basic styles for both
buttons and then extend this class into
button light and button dark and you'll
see what I like what I mean so I want to
display these as inline - block okay so
that they're on their own line and they
go all the way across and then padding
it'll say 0.5 REMS and let's do one REM
and border I'm going to set to zero no
border we want to have a margin bottom
of 0.3 REM and then I also want let's
see we want to hover effect so we're
gonna say in here and % hover and let me
just check this real quick yeah so if we
hover one we want the secondary color
for the hover so let's say right here
background we're gonna set that to the
secondary color and let's also set the
color to our set text color function and
pass in secondary color as the
background all right now we want to
extend this into button because remember
if we look at our HTML if we look at our
work HTML and we look at the buttons
it's BTN dark and BTN light we're not
using BTN at all
so in sass we can extend this class so
we want to go underneath it and say BTN
- dark and let's add BTN - light okay
now I want to take all of these styles
and import in bit not import but
extended into these so I can just simply
say at extend
and we want to extend the BTN class
alright so we want to put this in both
of these now if I save this now that
those styles are getting put on these on
both of these now what is different
about these is is obviously the colors
so we want to add separate colors so
let's do background so this is the the
button dark so I'm gonna do let's see
for a button dark let's say darkened
will say darken and we want to darken
the primary color and we want to darken
it by 50 all right and then let's set
the color of the text to 333 let's see
what that looks like that's not right
that's because this should be white
there we go
and then for this one let's just copy
what we just did here and go to the
light and instead of darken we're gonna
use lighten okay lighten primary color
by 50 and color for the text will be 333
and save there we go let's see that's
still not right you know what we don't
want to display:inline-block we want to
display as block there all right so
that's good that's what we want now if
we look at the other page it looks it's
identical but if we were to stretch this
stretch it out it stays at 3 I actually
want for 4 columns for items on big big
screens and then if we make it smaller
we want it to be too and then very small
one that's obviously not that's not
doable so we need to make this
responsive right so let's go to our
mobile dot s CSS this is where we make
everything responsive and let's let's
start with the extra-large because on
extra-large I want I want it to be 4
items per
so to do that we're gonna say dot
projects and we're going to just change
the grid template columns okay so we're
going to change it to repeat and instead
of three we want for fractional x' 1fr
so I'll save that and now if I make this
bigger it gets to four when it's like
whatever is whatever we set it to one
one seven one four extra large something
like that so that's that takes care of
the extra large for large screens I want
three so I guess I'll just grab this and
put it inside here and we'll just change
that to three whoops not to three okay
and then let's see for medium screens I
want it to be 2 so media media MD will
go to the bottom of that which ends here
so we want to make sure we're inside of
it and we're gonna change this to two
okay and then for small screens we just
want one fractional so we don't even
need to repeat we're just going to do
one fractional okay let's save so this
is a large screen or is this medium
medium is right here that's right so two
on medium when we get to small turns to
one and it's stacked awesome so now
that's completely responsive so that's
done let's go ahead and just do a quick
commit
get that all we're gonna get commits and
let's see we added the work page with
grid I'll just say work page and
responsiveness okay so now we want to do
is create the last page which is the
contact page which is pretty simple so
in our disk folder let's create a file
called contact dot HTML and basically
we're going to use flexbox for this just
to create these boxes so if we look at
the page here you can see our boxes so
let's copy from about grab everything
from about paste it in contact let's go
up to the top change it to contact me
and let's see let's move the current
class right here off of this nav item
onto the contact or how to reach me nav
item and then down here let's change the
ID from about to contact I'll change
this to contact and then me that's fine
let's see for the h2 we'll say this is
how you can reach me and then under that
we basically want to get rid of of
everything under that so actually what
I'll do is change the about info to a
div with the class of boxes and get rid
of everything within that div so that
div ends right there so let's grab
everything in it and get rid of it so
now we just have this box's div and in
each one it's going to be very simple we
have the email the phone and address and
we want the the heading like email
to be yellow at first so let's let's put
in an h2 here so div class boxes
actually want to div within here and
then know h2 I don't know why I said
that we just want a span with the class
of text secondary okay in here we're
gonna say email and outside of the span
we'll put let's say whatever John Doe at
test.com
so that's our email then we'll copy this
div let's close this UPS may give us a
little more room so let's copy this div
I'll do two more okay the second one is
going to be his phone number and then
this last one is gonna be the address so
I'm just gonna make an address up I'm
gonna say 50 Main Street say Boston Mass
Oh to 101 and that's it let's save if we
go and look at the page it's just gonna
look like that so we want to add some
styling to this so let's go to our main
dot s CSS and we want to go down to the
bottom let's see let's go right under
we'll go above the button styles let's
go right under the work projects page
and we'll say contact page
okay so we have a class of boxes right
so let's say boxes and we want this to
be a flex container so we want to say
display instead of grid we're going to
use flex now normally I'd probably use
grid because that's what we're using on
the other pages but I just wanted to
kind of throw this in here because I
want it to be just a mix of different
technologies but you guys can do what
you want with it after so we're gonna
say flex - wrap wrap so that when it
gets too big okay so like when they
don't fit it's going to just go like on
to the next line like that so we want it
to flex wrap we want to space the
content evenly in between so we can
justify content and we can say space
evenly
that's what we're gonna choose and then
I also want to align the items to the
center and then let's just do a margin
top for when they're stacked I want to
do a margin top of one rim I'm sorry not
wearing this stack this is for the
actual boxes so this is for the top here
alright so let's go ahead and save this
and see what happens so when you when
you do display flex it's automatically
going to align them this way all right
now we want to do each div within the
boxes class so in here we're gonna say
div and let's do a font size of let's
say - r m let's do a border of three
pixels white solid
let's do padding for padding will do 1.5
REMS and on the top and bottom in 2.5
excuse me on the on the left and right
and then let's do margin - bottom three
REMS for when they're stacked
okay now we're gonna have a hover effect
and I do want it to kind of to have that
ease out of transition so I am gonna add
that mix in here and include ease out so
now let's take care of the hover
actually let's save it see what it looks
like good so and you can see if if we
make this bigger it goes like that
okay so the wrap causes it to kind of
knock down so for the hover I want to be
inside the div and we want to do an
ampersand colon hover and let's do
padding 0.5 ram top and bottom
let's do 1.5 because what I want to
happen is when we hover I want the
padding to change I wanted to give I
want that that effect like that okay so
I'm changing the padding on hover and
you don't have to do this it's just
something just I don't know just
something to add
so 1.5 let's also change the background
to be the secondary color and let's see
we want the color of the text to be to
use that set text color function okay so
set text you can see we're using this
all over the place so set text color and
the its background is secondary color so
we want to put that in there okay and
then for the span because remember this
the email phone address that's inside of
a span and we don't want that to be
yellow we want that color to change as
well or else we won't see it with the
yellow with the secondary color
background so in here let's just say
span will nest this in here like that
and we'll simply say color we'll just
copy this use the set text color okay so
let's save that and now if we hover over
it you'll see we get that effect
okay make it bigger all right so pretty
simple and there's nothing we need to do
to make it more responsive because you
can see it just stacks automatically and
it looks good
alright so that's it guys whoops that
should actually go to whoa I guess that
was cached or something the home page
why is that going there let's let's um
let's change that why is that going
there it's because we need to actually
change it to go to index.html I believe
yes and I think we have it going to
slash yep let's change that so for each
menu item that is for the home right
here we have to change that to
index.html so that's contact let's go to
about change it here let's go to what
else do we have index
and work
alright you save that let's close these
up and I think I think that's it guys so
I'm just gonna make a quick commit
and I'm just gonna say initial website
finished okay all right so in the next
video what I want to do is deploy this
thing so we'll do that next and we
should be finished up