alright guys before we start working on
the about page I want to I want to
create a function for our set text color
because right now if we change the
primary color to let's say white any
light color the text is now unreadable
because we just set it we set the color
of the text to white now what I want to
do is create a function called set text
color now it has to be a function not a
mixin because if we want to return a
color from it and if you want to return
anything you it has to be a function not
a mixin so let's create this right below
the background mixin above the media
queries and we'll say set text color
okay and instead of doing at mixin we're
gonna do function like that and we're
gonna call it set - text - color and
it's gonna take in an initial color
variable so that'll be whatever the
background color is will pass in and
then we want to do an if statement so we
want to say if and we're going to test
the lightness so we can say if lightness
of the color we pass in is greater than
40 so if the lightness is greater than
40 then we want to return so at return
black as our color okay then we want to
do an else so at else then we want to
return white as our color okay and we'll
save that so whatever's passed in if the
lightness is greater than 40 it'll
return black if not it'll return white
now to implement this let's go to our
main dot s CSS let's go to the body and
see where we just we put white for the
color instead of putting white we're
gonna use our mixin so we're just going
to say here we need to include let's see
actually no I'm sorry we don't need to
include since it's a function we can
simply say set
text-color we should be able to just do
set text color and then pass in the
background color which is primary color
so let's save and there we go so now
it's black because the primary color is
a light color if I change the color to
the primary color back to what it was
which is a dark color now it's white now
we want to do the same for the menu icon
see if I save it now the menu icon is
not really visible so let's go to menu
dot s CSS go up to the button and later
we put the color so it's in the button
line right here wait a minute is that
where we want to put this yeah so let's
do instead of background because we're
not using color we're using background
but we set it to white so let's change
that to set text color and let's pass in
here the background I mean the primary
color which is the background color
technically and save and now that's that
color okay so we need to do the same for
the nav links so let's go down let's see
where are we going to do this
let's see nav lunk alright so we're
gonna do it here right now they're white
so we're gonna change it to set text
color pass in primary color save and
there we go alright so I think that
that's all the places we need to
implement this for now so I'm going to
change that back to the the dark color I
just don't want to do that let's change
this primary back to four four four and
there we go good so now let's create the
about page so I'm going to go to my dist
folder and we're gonna create a new file
called about dot HTML so if I go to my
navigation here and I go to about it's
good it's gonna give us this message
because in the menu and the index if we
go down to our links I have slash about
slash work we don't want that we
actually want to remove this slash in
order for this to work or else we'd have
to do like slash dist and we don't want
to do that so let's save that and make
sure we can navigate to a boat and there
we go so it's completely empty obviously
now each page is very similar in that it
has the the navigation at the top the
over excuse me the overlay in the header
the title and all that stuff so I'm
gonna copy everything that's in my
index.html I'm gonna grab all of it and
go to my about HTML and paste that in
okay and I'm just gonna close this up
close some of these files up up here and
let's work on this so I'm going to
change the title to just about me and
then the only thing in the menu that we
need to change is the current class
because right now it's on this list item
of the home item but we want it on the
about so we're gonna put that right
there
okay and then we'll go down here let's
change let's change the ID of main to
about and let's change this isn't going
to be a name anymore it's gonna be about
and then me will put in
side of the text secondary and then for
the SM heading let's just say let me
tell you a few things okay and we're not
going to have the icons so we're going
to completely get rid of this div right
here all right so now we're gonna add
our extra content and if we look at the
about page and the final project we can
kind of see what we're doing here so we
want basically this is going to be the
grid this is going to be where you're
going to use the grid system to align
this we have the bio image the bio and
then we have job 1 job 2 and job 3 we
also have a footer let me just quickly
add in the footer under the main tag I'm
gonna say footer and let's see I'm
actually going to give this an ID to of
main footer and we're gonna say
copyrights let's say copyright we'll put
in our HTML entity for a copyright
symbol and then 2018 or whatever year
you're watching this so back up here
under the h2 we're gonna have a div with
the class of about info ok so this is
going to be the class that we add the
grid to everything in this is going to
be a grid item first thing is the image
so let's say image I'm going to give it
a class of bio - image the source is
going to be in the image folder and then
portrait JPEG for the alt we'll just say
John Doe so under the image we want to
have a div with the class of bio and
inside here let's put let's put an h3
with the class of text secondary so that
we have that yellow color and say bio
like that and then we'll have a
paragraph which will have some sample
text with Emmet you can do lorem and
then the number of words you want so
I'll say 30 and then tab and it just
gives me a bunch of sample text 30 words
so under the bio the bio is our second
grid item the images the
first now we want the the jobs okay so
each one will have a class of job so
let's say dot job and let's say times
three and now we have three three jobs
actually it's not do that let's do one
at a time so we'll do a job this will
also have a class of job - one and then
inside each job we'll have an H three so
the first one will say one two three
webshop and let's do a paragraph with
lorem 20 okay 20 words so that's our
first job now we'll copy this div and we
want two more so one two SEC this one's
going to be job - this one's gonna be
job three let's just change up the word
the the title here we'll call this one
designers designers ABC stupid names but
doesn't matter well one thing I forgot
was the position we want an h6 with the
position so here let's say full stack
developer here we'll say h6
let's do front-end developer and then
this last one we'll change it to let's
do web works and then for the h6 let's
say we'll say graphic designer and you
can put years and stuff if you want if
you're gonna use this as your portfolio
you might want to just kind of you know
make it look a little better and add
some stuff but it doesn't really the
content doesn't really matter here so
let's save this and let's take a look at
our about page which looks horrible
oh the background image we don't want
that here so want to make sure we move
the ID remove the ID of BG image from
the body there we go okay so let's let's
align all this stuff using grid CSS so
we're gonna go to main dot CSS let's go
all the way down to the bottom and we're
going to use grid template area
is here so basically we can map out the
different areas and where we want them
displayed so first off let's take the
about - info and let's display that as a
grid and then we want to add our grid
- template areas and this is like a
visual representatives a visual
representation of what you want to
display so I'm gonna go on the next line
here put in some quotes and I'm gonna
say bio image bio bio that's gonna be
the first row second row is going to be
job one job - job three now if we look
at the final project here you can see
you can see how this is mapped to this
so bio image right here and then bio we
want to stretch across - ok across -
fractional x' that's going to be a three
fractional grid and then down here each
fractional has job 1 job 2 and job 3 so
so you have a visual representation of
it so next thing we need to do is define
the grid template columns and we want
basically three Fr so we could do one fr
one if I wanna far like that or we can
use a repeat so make it a little shorter
we can say we want to repeat three times
one fr like that okay now if we go back
to our site here and we save it's gonna
look like this and notice that the bio
isn't stretching across this job is up
here it's because we haven't defined
these grid tend these grid areas yet so
we're going to do that in a minute but
let's add some spacing so what I'm gonna
do is say grid gap and set 30 pixels and
save and now I have some spacing and our
next task is to create the grid areas so
first one is the bio image so it has a
class of bio image and we want to say
grid area is going to be bio image like
that should be whatever we at
whenever we put it as right here okay
and then we have the bio so class of bio
and we want to give that the grid area
of bio and then we have job - one is our
class and we want to set the grid area
of job one and I'm just going to copy
this because we have job two and job
three okay so two two and three okay now
there's some other styles I want to add
like for the image sheva semicolon so I
also want to margin Auto so you want a
margin Auto I want to set the border
radius because I want it to be rounded
so I'm going to do 50% and I also want a
border around the image which will be
the secondary color it's going to be
three pixels and solid alright and then
for the bio I also want to just up the
font size so I'm gonna say font size I'm
going to set it to 1.5 REMS and save and
there we go so now we have it aligned
properly let's see yeah so I think that
looks good let's make this a little
bigger see if that looks right yeah so
that should look right now the jobs I
want these to have like a little
background as you can see right here and
a little border at the bottom so each of
them have a class of jobs so we want to
style that so we'll say job and let's
say background and I'm gonna set the
background to just lighten which we'll
take in the primary color and then the
amount I want to lighten is five so if I
save that it'll look like that we want
to add some padding so it's not up
against the edge I'll say 0.5 REMS and
then let's add a border bottom of the
secondary color say 5 pixels and solid
and there we go all right so it looks
pretty good see what am I missing
I think that's good now for the foot are
the footer looks like crap so let's do
that oh and one thing that I didn't do
is I didn't nest all this stuff in the
about info you don't have to but I like
to use the nesting so I'm just gonna
grab all of this and put it inside of
the about info you don't have to though
it's however you want to structure it is
fine so for the footer let's see let's
go down here and let's say we gave it an
ID of main footer and let's do text
align to the center and let's add
padding of one R M let's make the
background dark so I'm gonna use darken
and I'm gonna pass in the primary color
and I'm gonna darken it by ten okay make
it a little darker and then color we
want it to we want to use our set text
color function okay and we want to pass
in the primary color as the background
so it'll be based on that and then the
height I'm going to set to sixty pixels
all right so let's save that and take a
look at it so that looks pretty good
now the issue is if our content didn't
go down all the way like if it ended
here this this footer would be up it's
up here and I can actually give you an
example of that so if we go to about and
we get rid of let's get rid of these
jobs right here and save and look at the
footer now so we want it to stick to the
bottom we want to create a sticky footer
so I'm just gonna put that back and to
create a sticky footer
it's not very difficult we can actually
use the calc function in CSS and we want
to use that
on the main okay so we want to use that
on the basically the element above it
which is the main right now if we go to
our main CSS and we go to the main class
we have a height of a hundred percent so
and that basically what that's going to
do is it's going to be a hundred percent
of the content that's inside of it
so if the content ends here that's where
it ends and the footer moves up so
instead of using a hundred percent I'm
going to comment this out and I'm gonna
say min height and I'm gonna set it to
calc so we want to calculate here a
hundred viewport Heights okay so we want
to take 100 V for tights minus the
height of the footer so 60 pixels and
let's save that alright now if we go to
our boat and we remove the jobs like we
just did the footer should stay at the
bottom hopefully so let's see these and
save and there we go so now we have a
sticky footer and before calc was
available it was kind of difficult to
get a sticky footer to stay in place but
that's all you have to do the the
element before it you just want to
calculate the viewport Heights - the
height of the hood and the footer okay
so back to our about page now if we make
this smaller it looks horrible okay and
what we need to do is add to our mobile
file mobile dot s CSS and we need to
basically change the orientation for
medium screens and down and what I mean
by orientation is or is it's this right
here the grid template areas instead of
like lining them like this we want them
all stacked on each other now one thing
that I just realized that I did wrong is
the mobile when we if we look at our
main sass file mobile we actually want
to include this at the at the very
bottom we want our media queries at the
bottom because we want them to run after
the initial CSS so we want to take that
and just move it to the bottom like that
okay and then let's go to mobile s CSS
let's make sure we're within the medium
media query and this is where the
brackets extension that I have is very
useful so we can tell that the yellow
one is where it ends
so we'll go right in here and let's say
about info and let's see so we basically
it's already displayed as a grid all
that stuff is we already did that we
just want to change a couple things we
want to change the grid template areas
okay we want to change the a let's go on
let's go on the next line put in some
quotes we want the bio image and we want
everything stacked on top of each other
than the bio then job 1 job 2 and job 3
ok now as we have it set we have the
template column set to 3 fr-s 1 fi R 1
if R 1 F R now since they're stacked we
just want one single fractional so we
want to change its put a semicolon here
and let's change the grid template areas
lot areas columns we want to change that
to just one single fractional okay let's
save and there we go so now everything
is stacked
okay so again visually this is exactly
what we're looking at here everything is
on top of each other so grid template
areas is very very powerful because you
can basically just map out what you want
where you want and you can get much more
advanced than this as well but that's
that's pretty much the gist of it
alright so once we hit a certain point
we go back to our other layout awesome
so I think that's it for the about page
so in the next video we're going to
start on the what do we have next
the my work page which will also be
using the grid except we're not going to
be using grid template I
areas we're just going to use grid
template columns so I'll show you how to
use the grid without using this I want
to kind of just show you different ways
of doing things on different pages we'll
also use a little bit of flex box on the
contact page alright so that's it I will
see you in the next video and actually
before we go let's go ahead and just
commit real quick again you guys don't
have to do this let's get and all get
commit and what do we do here so I can't
remember we just did the about page we
did the set text color so let's say text
color function and about page alright
okay guys so that's it I'll see you in
the next video