right guys in this video we're going to
work on the menu the menu button and all
that stuff but at first of all I want to
make a git commit because I forgot in
the last video and that's the problem
with using git in videos I always forget
because I'm just I'm just consumed with
teaching and what we're doing and
talking that I forget to do my commit so
it's not going to be the most organized
get process but let's just go to another
terminal here and we'll clear this out
and I'm just going to add everything so
I'm going to say get to add all and
let's say git commit dash M and I'll say
index mark up and main sass alright
alright so let's move on we'll go back
to the other terminal here and let's
make this smaller so for the menu we're
gonna have our own s CSS file for the
menu because there's gonna be quite a
bit of sass so let's create a new file
here called underscore menu dot s CSS
and then we want to of course bring that
in to the main s CSS so let's do import
menu like that alright and let's see
what we're gonna do first here so we
want to kind of build out the button
like I said it's going to be purely CSS
so in the menu file let's say a menu
button has a class of menu - BTN and we
want to position it absolute because we
want to say exactly where we want it to
be which is going to be over in the
corner and I also want it to always be
on top I'm going to give it a z-index of
3 so I want it to be very close to the
front and then from the right I'm gonna
say I want it 35 pixels and also from
the top we'll do 35 pixels and then when
we hover over it we should have a
pointer so we're going to
cursor:pointer and i want to give it
that that transition that ease out mixin
so that it transitions all of its
properties so we'll say @include and
let's say ease out like that actually
let me check something here yeah make
sure the menu is after the config so if
I save that we're not going to see any
difference here because the the menu
button has nothing in it except a couple
divs and those divs have the class of
BTN line so though that's what we want
to style next so inside within the class
of menu button let's create the BTN dash
line styling so I'm going to give it a
width of 28 pixels and let's give it a
height of 3 pixels remember this is each
line okay so if we look at the final
project each of these lines is this BTN
line so 28 pixels wide 3 pixels in
height and we want margin which is going
to be the space in between so I only
want margin on the bottom so we're going
to do top 0 top right bottom will be 5
pixels left 0 and let's set the
background to white and then let's also
include ease out on this so I want to
say include ease out and let's save what
is going on here wise
that that is that saving all right am i
having an issue with notes so let me
restart notes ass if you guys aren't
seeing any changes or anything just go
ahead and stop this with ctrl C and then
let's run NPM run sass again what is
going on we should be seeing it we
imported menu
why are we not seeing it let's let's
resave this I'll just save there we go
alright so now it's showing up so I
guess because it's a partial and we
included it for some reason it wasn't
updating so if you if you're not seeing
it just reset your your NPM run SAS and
then re-save the file so now we have our
button over here obviously it's not
gonna do anything we haven't added in
any any effects to it or anything yet
and we're going to have to use
JavaScript for that and we're going to
get into the JavaScript because I want
you to look at the final project and
let's look at the elements tab in the
dev tools alright so we want to check
out let's see the menu button class and
then the nav class menu and all this
stuff in between now watch down here
what happens when I click the when I
click the button see that the closed
class gets added here on the menu button
and then all of this other stuff gets
the class of show and when I click it
again that stuff goes away so that's
what controls is this this whole thing
here so we're gonna have to use
JavaScript to be able to make that
happen so let's go ahead and open up our
j/s inside the dist we want the j s and
then the main J's file and I'm just
gonna close that up and make this
smaller so we want to select items from
the Dom so let's say select Dom items
and by the Dom I mean a document object
model which is basically like the UI
structure all the HTML tags the
attributes all that stuff so we want the
menu button we want the entire menu
overlay the the nav list or the nav
items we want the branding all that
stuff so let's say Const we'll create a
variable called menu BTN and set that to
document we're gonna use the document
property here and there's a method
called query selector which will do just
that it'll select what whatever we put
in here we want to select the class
of BTN - menu okay so query selector
works just like jQuery in terms of
selection you can use classes or IDs or
just elements whatever you want any kind
of selector and then let's just copy
this down a couple times and we also
want the menu itself so create a
variable of menu grab the class of menu
we want let's see what else do we have
let's look at our index so we got the
menu button we got the menu we also want
the branding the menu nav and then each
nav item those should all be in
variables so here let's do menu nav
which is the UL so it has a class of
menu - nav and we want the menu branding
so that has a class of main menu
branding okay now for the nav items and
what I'm talking about is let's go over
here is each of these items here each of
these links now since there's more than
one we can't use query selector because
that will just grab the first one so we
need to use something called query
selector all which will take all of
those elements and put them into
something called a node list which is
similar to an array so let's call this
nav items and set it to document dot
query selector all this time and we want
the class of nav dash items okay so
that's our Dom selection now what we
want to do is set the initial state of
the menu so what I mean is the overlay
this right here we're going to create a
variable that represents if it's open or
closed but it will be set to true or
false so this will be true and then if
it's closed that's false we obviously
want it false by default so let's say
let show menu and let's set that to
false and I'm using let because we want
to directly reassign this
certain times and you can't do that with
con sconces for a constant so now we
need we need an event listener because
when we click this that's when we want
stuff to happen right so we're gonna say
menu button which were you defined above
we're gonna add an event listener on to
it we want to listen for a click event
and then once we click we want a
function to fire off called toggle menu
which we need to create so let's say
function toggle menu and we first of all
want to check the state of show menu we
want to see if it's false so if not
that's what the exclamation is not show
menu and then let's put an else here as
well so if the menu is not shown meaning
that that overlay this overlay right
here is not shown so this state here
then when we click this we want it to be
shown right so we want to add those
those show classes we also want to add
the closed class to the button because
that's what we're gonna that's what
we're going to use to make the X to make
that X form so let's first of all take
the menu BTN and in vanilla JavaScript
we can easily add a class by doing dot
class list dot add not ass not ass we
want class list add and we want to put
in the closed class okay so we're going
to add the closed class and then we can
just copy this down so this one here
will be menu and for menu we want to add
the show class okay everything else gets
show the only thing that wants that is
the closed class is the menu button so
show and show so want menu we also want
the menu nav to get that as well so menu
Navin
so menu branding ads show now the nav
links is a little different because the
nav links there's more than one and up
here we use query select all so the way
that we need to handle this is we need
to loop through all of the items and
then add the show class to each one so
we'll take nav items right and actually
I messed this up up here say oh I did
class nav items they actually have if we
look the class of nav items singular so
it won't work we need to change that to
nav items so nav items we're going to
use a for each here which is a high
order array method and we just pass in a
variable that we want to represent each
item and then I'm going to use an arrow
function here and I'm gonna take that
item for each one and then I'm gonna say
class list dot add and show okay so for
each nav item we want to add the show
class all right now else we actually
before we go into else we just want to
reset the menu state so now show menu
should be equal to true okay because now
it should be open now we want to do the
same we want to do this the opposite of
exactly what we did here in the else
okay so basically if the menu is shown
and we click it we then want to remove
all these classes so remove class let's
remove I'm just going to highlight this
add and do control D one two three to
select all those and then say remove
okay and then we just want to set this
back to false and that should be it
that should be all the JavaScript we
need so let's test it out let's open up
our dev tools here go to our elements go
to the header we want to see the menu
button actually we can leave that closed
but we want to see everything in here
and make sure that the menu button gets
the closed class and then everything
else gets show so let's go ahead and
click and nothing happens you cannot
read out of this out of it
know what oh this should be menu button
a new button alright let's try it again
let's go back to elements check this
stuff out
and let's click and there we go we get
clothes added to the menu button and
then everything else gets the show class
now if I click it again that stuff
should get removed let's click it again
and now it's gone all right so that's
the Java Script now obviously that
doesn't do anything in the UI that just
handles that that Dom manipulation to
handle the UI we need to use sass or CSS
so I think what we'll do now I don't
think we'll be able to fit the whole
overlay and the button transition and
stuff like that in this video but let's
at least take care of this this we're
how it turns into an X and back so let's
do that now remember when we click this
gets the class of clothes so that's what
we want a style so that's part of the
menu button so we want to go within this
dot menu button in the sass and go down
here make sure you're not within the
button line but outside of it but still
in menu button and then let's put a
comment here and we'll say rotate rotate
into X with menu lines so let's say
ampersand dot clothes because now we're
styling the menu button when it has the
class of clothes right so when it's
clicked and we want to say transform we
want to transform we want to rotate it
right so we want to rotate and then here
we can put a degrees we can put 180
degrees ok now if I save that and let's
see what happens when I click it just
rotates like that ok so that's part of
it
now we need to deal with each line
because each line we need to basically
reposition the second line we're
actually going to get rid of and we're
going to take the top and bottom and
make an X with it so it's actually kind
of cool so let's go down here and then
say dot VTN - line okay because we want
to deal with the button lines and we
want to basically select each one and we
can use a pseudo selector called enth
child to select each one so let's say
line 1 line 1 is going to rotate let's
say line 2
we're gonna hide line 2 and then line 3
is also gonna kind of rotate all right
so let's handle the second one actually
no let's just go ahead and start here so
we're gonna say ampersand : nth - child
and we want the first line so we put
into one here okay
and just to show you this works we'll
say let's change the background color so
we'll say background red and save now if
I click this notice that the top line it
does the rotation and the top line turns
to red when the closed class is added
and when I go back it goes away so what
we want this to do is just rotate and
may put it make it go in a diagonal
fashion so we can use transform rotate
and then we use translate to kind of
position it and you can look up these
properties like CSS let's say transform
and the Mozilla site has is really good
for this so right here
alright so when it gives you an example
did you see that transform let's say
let's say 1.5 let's see how to see that
how it changes so you can transform we
can translate which repositions it and
we can put this wherever we want if we
change this to and this is x and y
values if we put a hundred it moves over
if we put zero moves over so translate
just repositions it and then rotate
turns it so we want to use a combination
of those to create this effect so let's
say let's get rid of this obviously we
don't want that
and we'll do transform say rotates we
want to rotate 45 degrees because
remember we're making an X and then we
want to translate which will just kind
of reposition it to five pixels five
pixels all right let's save that and see
what we get so if we click there we go
so the first line you can see has
repositioned itself using rotate and
translate okay so that's what we want
for that line the second line we want to
completely hide so I'm gonna copy this
and change this to two because that's
gonna grab the second line and we're
simply going to change the opacity to
zero which will just basically just make
it go away I'll hide it all right so
let's save that let's try it and there
we go so the second line is now hidden
now we want to deal with the last one we
want to make that one go this way okay
so let's copy this and let's go down
here and paste that in we'll change this
to three because we're working on the
third line this time we want to rotate
negative 45 we want it to go the other
way
and then we're going to change the
translate position to seven and then
negative six okay and it took me a
little while messing around with these
values to get it to look like an X but
that's what I came up with so let's save
let's go over and click and there we go
so now each line has the middle one is
gone and then the top one is going this
way and the bottom one is going this way
so CSS transitions are very very
powerful okay you can do a lot in terms
of animation and stuff especially you
know you have to add a little bit of
JavaScript so that you can add and
remove classes and stuff like that but I
think that's a pretty cool effect and I
think that X looks good but if you want
to try to reposition it a little you can
do that you can mess with the values you
can make it thicker whatever you want to
do is fine but I think we're going to
end the video
here guys in the next one we're gonna
work on the overlay so we want to work
on this whole part here okay before we
do that though let's go ahead and do our
commit so let's go to this terminal here
and we'll say get add I'll get commit
and it's do dash M and what do we do
here we did the menu button we did the
JavaScript and we did the rotate
I will save me a menu button JavaScript
and rotate all right good
all right so that's it guys I will see
you in the next video where we'll start
to create the overlay