alright guys in the last video we just
can't kind of give you an intro to the
project and we also created our SAS
workflow so I have nodes SAS running
right now so I'm just gonna make this a
little smaller and we're gonna just
create our index HTML markup which which
isn't that much basically if we look at
the finished project here this is the
header this area up here with the menu
button also everything in this overlay
will go in the header and then this is
the main content here so it's just split
up into two parts basically so let's go
over to index.html let's get rid of this
h1 and let's create a header tag and
inside here we're gonna have the menu
button remember I said it's gonna be all
CSS so we're gonna have a class of menu
- BTN and inside here we want three divs
with the class of BTN - line oops BTN -
line so I'm going to use Emmet here and
do times 3 and hit tab and it'll give me
three of them so each of these divs
represents one line in this little icon
thing now under the div but still in the
header we want to create a nav with the
class of menu ok and this is going to be
broken into two parts so we have this
side with this side which is menu
branding this side is menu nav so let's
create a div here called with the class
of menu branding and then under that we
want a UL with the class of menu - nav
so the menu branding this is actually a
background image it's not going to be an
inline image tag so it's just going to
be a div with the class of portrait ok
and we'll put the image in through CSS
and then in the UL we just want a bunch
of allies so these lis are going to have
a class of nav - item and inside here
we'll have an a tag with the class of
nav - link okay and this is going to go
to slash and then the text inside the a
tag is just going to say
home like that and I'm just gonna close
this up may give us a little more room
okay so we want to copy this Li down so
we can do a new shift option down or
shift alt down on a1 windows so one two
three because we went four all together
this second one will go to about dot
HTML we're going to change the text to
about me and then this one here we'll go
to work dot HTML we'll change this to my
work and then this last one here will go
to contact dot HTML and we'll change
this to how to reach me
all right so that's our header so if we
save this and we take a look it's gonna
look absolutely horrendous because we
have no CSS yet and you know hTML is
just very very ugly without CSS so under
the header we're gonna put the main area
so though I'm gonna put this in an html5
main tag so it's same main and inside
here we'll have actually before we do
that let's give this an ID of home each
page I want to have its own ID and then
for the main tag and then if we take a
look at the project here I want this to
be a heading and this to be this to be
an h1 this to be an h2 with their own
classes so h1 this is going to have a
class of LG - heading like that and
we'll say John Doe and then we're gonna
have an h2 underneath which will have
the class of SM - heading so small
heading and in here we're gonna say web
developer programmer designer and
entrepreneur so entrepreneur I'm a
horrible speller what is it PR e and was
he you are I'm a horrible speller
alright so web developer program our
entrepreneur
what else do we want to do here now
notice how the last name is a different
color so I'm gonna wrap the the last
name in a span with the class of text
- secondary because that color is
actually going to be the secondary color
in our SAS in our SAS variable so we
just want to move the span right here
like that okay and if we save this and
take a look it's gonna look like this
now for the icons we're gonna need the
font awesome icon library so we want to
head over to font awesome comm and you
want to go to this is the responsive
version so we'll hit that menu and then
go to use on the web getting started and
then grab this link right here okay so
we're gonna grab that and put that in
our index page at the top in the head
right above where we put the CSS file in
so that'll allow us to use the icons
okay so I'll close that up close this up
as well and then down back down here
under the h2 we're going to put a class
a div with the class of icons and let's
put in a link and I'm not gonna have
these links go anywhere but obviously
you would have them go to the person's
profile like their Twitter profile and
so on the first icon is going to be
Twitter so we want an eye tag with the
class of F a B and then also a class of
FA - Twitter and with Emmet we can do
that like this and hit tab okay so
that'll give us the Twitter icon let's
save make sure it works good so I want
this to be a little bigger so with font
awesome we can add the class of FA - 2 X
and save and it gets a little bigger you
can also do 3 X for X but we want to X
so I'm going to take this copy this down
3 more times
second one is going to be Facebook third
one will be LinkedIn and the last one is
going to be github
okay so we'll save that now we have our
four icons do it now the last thing we
want on this page is just a link to our
JavaScript file which we haven't even
created yet so let's go right above the
body and put in a script tag with a
source attribute that points to J s /
main j s and we might as well create
that so let's go into dist okay make
sure you're in dist create a folder
called J s and inside J s create a file
called main dot J s and we're not going
to touch that just yet all right so
that's our HTML that's all we need on
this page so we can actually close this
up now
let's head over to our main dot s CSS we
can close that package.json up so the
first thing I want to work on as far as
our CSS or sass is just like the core
the core styling now I want to add a
border box I'm sorry a box sizing
property for everything so if you want
to select everything in CSS you use the
asterisk and we want to set box sizing
to border box which will just take a
little make it so that if we have
padding on anything like padding on the
inside it's not going to affect the the
height the width or the height of it
it's just going to be it's just going to
be within the box model so we want to do
that and then in the body we want to
make sure that it has a height of a
hundred percent at all times we want to
take the margin away so margin zero and
as I save this will take effect now the
font we obviously don't want Times New
Roman so let's change the font family
and let's change it to this Segoe UI and
then to homogeneous sans serif so I'm
gonna save that you see the fonts
changed let's see what else do we want
to do here let's let's change the line
height so basically the space between
lines I'm going to put 21.5 and save and
I think that's all we want to do here as
far as the body so
below it let's take care of the headings
so we'll put a comment in here we'll say
headings
let's do h1 h2 h3 should be commas h2 h3
and for all headings
I want no margin so I'm gonna set margin
zero when I save you'll see that that
margin gets it disappears and then I'm
also gonna add a font weight I don't
want it to be I don't want it to be that
thick so I'm gonna say font - weight and
we'll set it to 400 save and now you can
see it's it's much thinner so with sass
what we can do instead of doing like h1s
going down here and doing h1 dot LG -
heading like we would with regular CSS
we can go inside here and we can nest
now we don't want to just do dot LG -
heading because what this is referring
to is a class of LG heading within an h1
h2 or h3 we want it to be attached to it
because if we look at our HTML we're get
it we want the h1 that has LG heading as
its own class not nested within it so
what we do is we just add an ampersand
in front of this okay so that's going to
be the same as doing h1 dot LG heading
or h2 h3 dot LG heading and for this we
want to set the font size to 6 REM okay
so I'm gonna save that and it's gonna
get really big now if you don't know
what a REM unit is it's basically a
multiplier of the the HTML tags font
size so the font size of this right here
alright and its default font size is 16
pixels so unless you you declare it here
as something else it's going to be 16
pixels now one REM is going to be 16
pixels if we have 6 REMS
that's going to be 6 times 16 okay and
start in terms of font size and I can
show you this in the chrome tools so if
we open up our chrome tools with
command option I or f12 on Windows and
we go down here to our CSS let's
actually use this tool right here to
select the h1 you can see font size 6 R
M we already know that we can see that
here but on this side you can see the
computed properties and if you look at
the font size it's 96 pixels because 16
pixels times 6 is 96 now if I were to
declare my HTML font size here so let's
say font size and let's say 10 pixels
and save now you can see the computed
size is 60 pixels because now that it's
10 6 r m is going to equal 6 times 10
rather than 6 times 16 ok so hopefully
that makes sense and I have a video on
my channel that talks all about r m and
m units and vh and BW and stuff like
that
mmm units are basically the same thing
except it doesn't go on the HTML element
it goes on the parent element of
whatever you're styling it goes on that
font size all right so let's let's also
add here actually that's all we want I
just want to change the font size and
then for the small heading let's do
ampersand dot SM - heading for this I
want to get rid of the margin bottom
let's do margin bottom I'm sorry not get
rid of it add to it I want to add to R M
which is going to be 32 pixels save that
and you can see it kind of pushed that
the icons down and then I'm going to add
in just an overall padding okay so I'm
going to say padding
let's do 0.2 RAM on the top and bottom
and let's do one rim on the left and
right all right now the reason I'm doing
that is because I'm actually giving it a
little background if we look at the
finished project see how the the heading
has a little background that's slightly
lighter so what we'll do is we'll say
background and with sass we have
something called lighten that we can use
so lighten takes in two parameters one
is the the orig
color which in our case is the primary
color and then how much we want to
lighten it so I'm going to say 0.5 and
if I save that you'll see that actually
you can't see that can you background
what I do I do wrong here
I'm not 0.5 - there we go
alright so now you can see that we have
that that background and we can see the
padding the space between now we're
going to have a background image at
least we're going to have the ability to
so we want to be able to kind of see
through this and we can't do that like
this right now it's just going to
completely block out the image to be
able to see through it we want to wrap
it in an RG be a function okay so we
want to wrap this again like that and
then put a comma here and then 0.5 is
the opacity that we want
okay so I'll save there'll be no
difference now but you'll see the
difference when there's an actual image
all right so that's that's it for the
headings now let's just move on to the
links so all links I want the color to
for now be white and I want to take away
the ugly underline so text - decoration
we're going to set to none okay so looks
a little better now let's work on the
header okay so for the header we're
gonna set the position to fixed because
I want I want the header to always stay
at the top okay so the headed by the
header I mean this right here where the
menu button is I always want that to be
at the top even if we have to scroll
okay so for instance if we go here
actually let me just yeah so if I scroll
you can see how it stays stays at the
top if we don't make that fix it's not
going to stay so header fixed we're
gonna put a z-index of two just so it's
always up front basically a z-index is
how close to you an element is so if we
put like a z-index of 1 it would be
behind as the index of 0 would be behind
so the bigger the number the closer
towards you it is and then let's set the
width of the header to a hundred percent
so it kind of just stretches across the
whole screen okay and since we set it to
fix now everything is basically like
pushed under it now the text secondary
we might as well take care of that texts
- secondary so we want to set the color
of this to a variable that we haven't
actually created yet so let's create
another variable called secondary color
- color and that's going to be it's
going to be a yellow color it's going to
be a hexadecimal value of EEC e1a okay
so that's the color we want for
secondary and then down here for color
will just add secondary color save and
now we get our little yellow last name
so now let's deal with the main so if we
look at the main tag that's everything
that's not in the header so that the h1
the h2 the icons so we want to add some
styling for that so let's say main and
we're gonna add padding let's add
padding all around a 4 R M so if I save
that it's going to just do 4 R M around
everything okay that's in the main and
let's set the height to 100% and then we
want to style the icons because right
now the icons there they're just too
close together and also I want the hover
to be the secondary color if we go to
the file project here and we go to the
homepage and we hover over them we get
the secondary color so inside main
because we can do nesting here we're
going to say dot icons so since we're
nesting it this is only going to affect
the class of icons inside of a main tag
that's how this works so let's add
margin top I want to just push them down
a little bit so I'm gonna say margin top
one rim push them down and let's add for
each for each icon its wrapped in an a
tag right so we want to put an
in here oh yeah so if we look here
inside the div class icons each icon is
wrapped in a link in an a tag so for
each one we're gonna add some padding
let's do padding of 0.4 REM and save and
now you can see there's some space in
between each one now for the color I
only want it to be on the hover so we
can go inside this a tag and we can use
ampersand and then colon hover okay
which is the same as doing like in
regular CSS just a colon hover like that
and then on hover we want the color to
be secondary so let's say secondary
color and let's save that so now when I
hover over it we get the yellow here all
right now we're gonna want to do some
transitions and transitions and CSS
basically it's just it's taking time to
do something whether it's fate whether
it's bringing in something from a
position like fade come bringing it in
from somewhere moving it around or what
else changing colors changing opacity so
you can fade stuff in that's what a CSS
transition does so if we add to this
hover right here let's see what do I
want to do let's let's say transition
and let's say we want in that the first
parameter is what you want to transition
so basically we're just transitioning
the color but I'm gonna say also
basically all anything that is
transitional okay and then the next is
going to be the time it takes so I'm
gonna say 0.5 seconds so a half a second
and then the next is is like the the
motion I guess which is we're gonna do
ease out okay so it kind of slowly eases
out now I save this and we go and we
hover over you can see it just kind of
fades in see how that it instead of just
going right to yellow it fades and
actually if I make this a bigger number
maybe you can see it better
we'll do 1.5 and see it fade in so
that's basically what the transition is
doing now I could just put color here
like that because that's basically the
only thing that we're transitioning
that's the only property that there is
here but what I want to do is set it to
all because I'm going to create a mix in
because we're going to be using this
this same thing the same transition for
a lot of different things so I'm going
to go up here to the top and I'm gonna
do at mix in which is basically like a
function and call this ease out okay so
we're going to say mix in ease out and
then let's take that transition so this
whole thing this whole line right here
I'm going to just cut that and I'm going
to put that up here like that and then
all we have to do to use it is go down
here and we can simply do at actually
I'm sorry I want to do include so when
you use a mix in you want to do at
include and then the name of the mix in
which is ease out like that so let's
save and we should get that same effect
so we get that that ease in except I
want to change it back to 0.5 not 1.5
that's too long
so 0.5 so now anytime we want to add
this transition to anything we'll just
go ahead and add this instead of
repeating the same thing and that's what
variables and mix-ins are good for
alright so I think that's pretty much it
for like the oh you know what we want to
do is we want to move this down because
if we look at the final project notice
how light the heading and stuff is
pushed down more than the inner pages
see how that these are up higher so
remember we gave the main and ID
we gave it an ID of home so inside main
I want to be inside main but not inside
anything else so it would be right here
we're just gonna do ampersand ID home so
many main that has the idea of home this
is going to affect so I just want to set
the overflow to hidden because I don't
want to have any scroll bars ever on the
homepage it should always it should
always not have scroll bars that's what
that's going to do and then the h1
inside the main tag with the idea of
home I just want to add a margin - top -
and I'm gonna set it to 20 VH and save
let's go back to ours and you can see it
got moved down now VH is another unit
just like REM and M basically it stands
review port heights and you can think of
it as and I've said this before think of
the height as a hundred slices across so
if you say 20 VH it's gonna take 20 of
those slices and that's that that's what
this is if you said a hundred VH it
would take up the whole thing
if you said fifty VH it would take up
half it would take up 50 of those 100
slices there's also V W which you could
think of the slices going to up and down
and a hundred would be the whole hundred
if it was fifty it would be 50 of those
100 okay so hopefully that makes sense
that's that's I think it was I think it
was Travis from dev tips that gave that
explanation and that that just made a
lot of sense to me so that's that's what
I use to explain those units so now what
I want to do is take care of the the
background image so we're gonna create a
variable up here called show - home -
image and that's going to be set to true
by default and I also want to put the
actual image in a variable so home image
which will be URL and I'm gonna we need
to get the actual image now I'm gonna
include the code in the description so
you can go ahead and grab that and
that'll include the image so I'm going
to go in my disc four and I'm just going
to create a new folder here and call it
IMG and then grab the images and bring
them over so in in your code you should
have whoops let me just copy these
so you should have background JPEG which
is the background to portraits one his
portraits small and then projects which
includes all the the images for the my
work page so you want to get those in
your disk colder in an IMG folder so now
I'm going to include the background
image here which is going to be dot dot
slash because we want to go outside of
the CSS folder and then into IMG and
then into the image name which is
background dot jpg all right hat jpg and
then the last variable I want here is
the opacity let me just close this
sidebar up here so we're gonna do
background - opacity and we're going to
set that to 0.9 all right so now let's
handle the actual background now there's
going to be a lot of stuff like we need
to check to see if the home if show home
image is true if it is then we want to
include the background we also need an
overlay because we don't want just the
image we won't be able to read the text
we need this we need this gray overlay
or whatever the primary color is as an
overlay so I don't want to do all that
stuff inside here in the body so I'm
going to create a special mix in for it
so we're going to say mix in and we'll
call it background and then we're just
going to include that inside the body so
include and then background yeah
actually we do that and yes we actually
don't need the parentheses so it saved
that so in this mix in here we first
want to check to see if the image is
actually enabled because if it's not
then we don't we don't want to do
anything else it should just be just
like this but if it is so we'll say if
actually we need to do a tiff in sass
and then we want to do show at the
variable of show home image
okay so if showhome image is true then
we want to take the BG image remember we
gave the eye the body and idea of BG
image we want to take that so we're
gonna say ampersand
ID BG - image okay and this is gonna
work because this mixin is being placed
in the body so it's going to look at the
body and it's going to look at any ID of
BG image and then we're going to set the
background to the home image we have it
in a variable so let's go ahead and save
that and there we go so we get the
background as an image now I want to add
the background let's see I'm gonna add a
couple properties here background
attachment we want to set that to fixed
and see how it's only showing part of
the image we want to set the background
size backgrounds not position size we
want to set that to cover okay we want
to cover the entire space so let's save
and there we go now obviously this is
this is not acceptable the text is
pretty much unreadable so we need to
have what's called an overlay and we
could crew we could put another element
inside here inside the body and we could
call it overlay and save it and then go
back and inside here we could add in dot
overlay okay so overlay inside the body
actually we would want the overlay in
the BG image body so we want to put that
here like that and the overlay we want
to give it a position of absolute okay
so we want it to basically cover the
entire thing we want it to cover this
whole the whole body and to do that we
want to start at the zero top so
basically top 0 right 0 so we're going
to start right here top right 0 we want
to go over 100
and up and down a hundred cent so let's
do with 100% and let's do height 100% so
if I go ahead and save this nothing's
gonna happen because we have no
background here for the overlay now if I
say I want a background and I use the
primary color and save what happens is
the color is now over the image and we
can't see the image so we have to use an
RGB a value which is red green blue
alpha and it allows us to have a color
but also have an opacity so you can see
through it now in SAS we can actually
wrap this primary color in our GBA so we
can go like that and then our GBA takes
in a color and then a second value of
the opacity now remember we have a
variable called background opacity so
I'm going to put that in and save and
there we go now we have a problem here
and can you see what that is the text is
behind the overlay now remember the Z
index to Z index took the higher the
number the closer it is to you so this
overlay I want to push behind the the
content the text here so we want to set
a Z index so I'm gonna say Z - index and
I'm gonna save it to a negative number
just to make sure that it gets pushed
back so let's set it to negative one and
save and there we go so now the text
moves up front okay so if we wanted to
change the opacity we could simply say
like 0.5 and save and there we go
but I like nine now one thing we could
do to just to save a little markup here
is this class of overlay we don't
actually need this because we can use
something called a pseudo element we can
use an after pseudo element so if I get
rid of this overlay right here okay
obviously that's everything's going to
go away the styling I want to change
this from being a class of overlay to
being as a pseudo element of
there : after so we can say hamper simp
and then : after now whenever used
before or after you put in a Content
variable and you can actually insert
content before or after whatever it is
in this case the BG image the body with
the idea of BG image now I don't want
any Content that should be a semicolon I
don't want any content so I'm just gonna
put an empty string here just just just
some quotes so let's go ahead and save
that and we get the same effect
so it essentially put in a pseudo
element something that's not actually in
the HTML but the CSS treats it like an
actual element that's after this element
hopefully that makes sense it's really
hot it's actually pretty hard to explain
but I think this is cleaner because we
don't have to actually have an overlay
div inside of our HTML all right so I
think that's going to be it for this
video guys we pretty much have the the
home page done except for a couple other
things that relate to all pages not just
the home page so in the next video I
want to start to work on the menu this
is going to be probably the the most
difficult part of the project we're
going to use quite a bit of sass we're
actually going to create a separate file
well that's speaking of that let's do
one more thing before we go see how we
have all these variables and mix-ins
right in our main s CSS let's put this
in a different file because this is
getting really messy so let's create a
new file and this is gonna be a partial
so partial should start with an
underscore and then we're gonna call
this config dot s CSS and then we'll
take all the variables and mix-ins out
so I'm going to cut those out and let's
put these in config and save now if I
save main dot s CSS it's going to
actually give us a bunch of errors down
here because it's looking for stuff that
is no longer here so we want to import
one import our config file and to do
that we simply do at import and then
inside of quotes we put in the name of
the file not the underscore or the dot
CSS just
it's config and let's save and now
everything's back okay and this is much
cleaner because all of our variables and
stuff are now held in the config file
all right so that's it guys in the next
video we'll start on the menu