[Music]
hey what's going on guys in this project
or this is the series I should say we're
gonna be building a responsive portfolio
website from the ground up okay so this
is a little different than most of my
series most of my series we build some
kind of small application using the
framework or something like that we're
going to build this just html5 css3
we're gonna use sass which is a CSS
pre-compile err and a little bit of
vanilla JavaScript so no frameworks no
bootstrap nothing like that and even if
you're a beginner if you just if you're
just starting HTML CSS JavaScript I
still encourage you to go through this
series and code along with me and I
think you're gonna learn a lot because
we're gonna use things like NPM which is
the node package manager to install node
sass which is our sass compiler and even
if you have no clue it's asses still
watch it and I'm gonna explain things
step-by-step I want this to be beginner
friendly as well as fun for intermediate
web developers alright so let's take a
look at the actual project before we do
anything so it's very minimalistic as
you can see the home page has a
background image it has an overlay and
then we just have the name a slogan and
some social media icons okay so the
coolest thing about this website is the
menu now this button is pure CSS and if
I click it you'll see it just rotates
into an X and back we're gonna do that
with css3 transitions and the transform
property and then we have this overlay
with the image on this side and the menu
on this side and the menu kind of floats
in from the right - as you can see and
then the about page is very simple and
we're actually going to use grid CSS
here we needs grid template areas so
you'll learn a little bit about that and
if we look at the my work page again
grid CSS here this is going to be
responsive as well which I'll show you
in a second and then the contact page is
very simple we're actually going to use
flex here I wanted to switch it up a
little bit and we have these little
hover effects from using CSS transitions
all right so let's take a look at the
responsiveness so if we go down to about
here that's probably like around the
size of a mobile device
and you can see everything is centered
looks nice and if we click on the menu
it's now in a vertical fashion rather
than horizontal so this is completely
responsive as well if we go to the about
page everything is nice and stacked and
neat if we go to the my work everything
is stacked same thing with the contact
all right and if we go to the my work
page
there they're all in basically one you
know one project per row if I go a
little bigger turns into two little
bigger to three and the biggest is gonna
be four okay so that's pretty much it
for the project it's not like it's not a
huge website but there's actually a lot
that goes into it especially when we get
into like the sass and the transitions
and stuff like that so you're gonna
learn a lot now let's take a look at the
structure real quick just so you can
kind of get an idea of what we're doing
so I have notes ass running down here
which is just compiling any sass that we
create all of our sass goes into the S
CSS folder as you can see here we have a
cup some partials we have a config file
where we can change the colors and we
can change if we want to not show the
image we can say false and you can see
the image goes away we can change the
opacity if we change that to 0.5 now the
image is more prominent if we whoops if
we want to change the colors well change
the the primary to white now notice the
text is white right now because it's on
a darker it's a primary color was dark
if I change the primary color to a light
color and then let's change this to I
don't know blue or something oops yeah
and then save now the text is dark
because we're actually going to create a
SAS mixin that will make the text dark
if it's on a light background and light
if it's on a dark background and we can
look around the site now and you can see
all the the primary and secondary color
changes so it still looks pretty good so
you can use any color scheme you want
but I'm going to go back to the dark
grey and the yellow and if you guys want
to use this as your actual portfolio
that's fine I mean this is completely
open-source the only thing I ask is that
you don't sell it you can
use it in any other way that you want
all right now in the dist folder is
basically what you would deploy to your
host we have the compiled CSS and then
our HTML Javascript in any images okay
so that's the dist folder and that's
pretty much it the rest of this stuff is
just your package jason will create our
SAS script here so it's not going to be
too difficult but it is like a
modernized project so hopefully you guys
enjoy it alright so in this video what
we're going to do aside from this
introduction is we're going to set up
our workflow so we want to install node
SAS you want we want to set it up so
that when we create any SAS in our CSS
folder here it gets compiled into our
distal der so we just want to set up a
workflow and structure and and then
we'll move to actually start you know
writing our HTML and stuff like that
alright so let's get started alright so
I'm gonna go ahead and leave the the
finish project open in case we need it
for reference so I'm gonna leave that in
this tab now there's a couple things
you're gonna need for this project
obviously you need a text editor and if
you have something that you've been
using that's fine but what I would
recommend is vs code or Visual Studio
code it's incredibly intuitive and fast
and easy to use it has great extensions
and and it's just it's definitely the
best text editor that I've ever used and
it's very very popular in the web dev
community it's completely open-source
so if you're on Windows Mac Linux
doesn't matter so that's what I'll be
using I'll also be using a couple
extensions so if you want to follow
along to a tee then I would definitely
recommend it you're also gonna need
nodejs installed and nodejs is a
JavaScript runtime but it the reason
we're installing it is because it comes
with something called NPM or node
package manager and the compile tool
that we're using for sass is called node
sass and we need NPM to install it so
that's the reason that you're gonna need
this and I know a lot of you guys
probably already have it installed but
go ahead and download it install it you
can use the latest version that's what I
usually grab or you can use the
long-term support version whatever you
want is fine
and then lastly I would recommend that
you have git which is version control
should have this on your system anyway
and if you're using Windows this comes
with a nice command-line tool or
terminal tool called git bash which
gives you some UNIX tools and it's
really nice and whenever I use Windows I
use get bash so you might want to
install that as well alright so and
we're going to be using it a little bit
get a little bit in this course or in
this series so let's uh let's go ahead
and close these up I already have all
the stuff installed I just wanted to
kind of show you so let's go let's let's
open up vs code in a new project so
first of all I'm gonna create a new
project folder now I'm gonna use the
terminal here and if you're if you're
brand new to this stuff
don't let the terminal scare you it's
not bad we're not doing anything
advanced just go ahead and open it up
and let's create a new directory to work
and so mkdir for make directory and I'm
gonna call this modern underscore
portfolio and then we're gonna CD so
change directory into modern underscore
portfolio and from here I want to open
up my visual studio text editor or
visual studio code I should say so to do
that I can say code and then dot which
represents the current folder now this
may not work for you if it doesn't then
you can open up vs code and just go to
your command palette which I believe is
shift command P and then type in shell
and then right here you can see it says
install code command in path so if you
click that you'll get this little
success message down here and then you
should be able to use that that code
command but you don't need to use the
terminal to open a folder you can simply
click on open file over here and then
open your folder it doesn't matter all
right so now what we'll do is create
some of our actually before we do that I
want to go over my extensions and vs
code that I'll be using so first off we
have live server which allows us to open
our HTML on a dev server that has auto
load so I won't have to keep reloading
the page highly recommended for any kind
of
just like static website development I'm
also using bracket pair colorizer which
is completely optional but I like it
because it matches colors of brackets
and curly braces and parentheses so that
you don't get lost if you have like a
lot of nested if statements and stuff
like that and this will also work in
sass as well as JavaScript but you don't
need it but something that I use and
then prettier is a code formatter so
it'll format HTML Javascript CSS and I
have it so that when I save my file it
automatically formats now it won't do
that by default if you want that to
happen if you want it to get to format
your code on save like I do then you
have to go to settings in vs code so you
can do ctrl comma or command comma or
just go to the little gear and then
settings and let me close this up and
then the setting that you're going to
need is this right here where is it
editor dot format on save that needs to
be set to true so what you would do is
just search for editor dot format and
it'll pop up on the left side over here
so right here format on save just click
this click true and then it'll get put
over here and then you just want to save
it with ctrl s or command s ok that's
really the only setting that you need to
kind of do what I'm doing here all right
so if you are using vs code I would
suggest those those extensions and in
that setting and you should be pretty
much identical to my environment alright
now first thing I want to create is my
disk folder so I'm going to create a new
folder called dist and like I said this
is where all of our HTML goes all of our
compiled CSS our JavaScript our images
stuff like that so I'm just going to
create an index dot HTML file in here
and I mean I'm going to be using Emmet
which comes with visual studio code and
it just makes for quick HTML like if you
want to do a class on an h1 you could do
h1 dot test tab gives you a class of
tests if I wanted to do like an ID of
hello I could say
hello tab gives me an ID and if you want
a div you don't even have to do you
don't even have to write if you can just
do like hash test tab and it gives you a
div with the idea of test now you can
create a boilerplate and HTML
boilerplate with exclamation and then
tab and it gives you your head body tags
it gives you your viewport meta tag for
a responsiveness so it's really handy
and in our title I'm just gonna say
welcome to my portfolio and in the body
for now let's just put an h1 and we'll
just say hello so let's save this now
you can open this up by just going to
your file system and opening up the the
HTML file but I'm gonna use live server
so you can right-click or control-click
and you can go to open with live server
and then it will open in your browser
okay and this is Auto refresh or auto
reload if I were to let's make this a
little smaller here if I were to let's
like add an exclamation and then save
right away it's gonna reload so it's
very very handy so now what I want to do
is create a folder outside of my dist
called scss okay because we want to want
to start to work on our sass workflow so
in here will be our sass files so I'm
going to create a file called main scss
ok this will be our main sass file any
other files we create will be partials
that we basically import into this file
now we need a way like I said for our
sass to get compiled down to regular CSS
because the browser doesn't read s CSS
files so for that we're using something
called node sass so this is the github
page and it uses libsass which is the C
version of of the of the preprocessor
and it's very very fast so it's another
reason I really like it now in order to
install node sass we need to use NPM as
you can see right here so before we
actually install node sass we need to
create something called a package.json
file which is basically like a manifest
for our project and to do that we can do
it with
p.m. in it now you can go to your
standard terminal like this or you can
open up the vs code integrated terminal
which is what I'm gonna do we can go to
view integrated terminal or you can just
do ctrl or command backtick and it will
you can toggle it all right so let's run
NPM in it and it's just gonna ask us
some questions package name that's good
version good description let's say
responsive portfolio website that's fine
everything else is fine if you want to
put your name here you can do that and
I'll give it an MIT license and enter so
that's going to create this file here
package Jason which is just that
adjacent file with some key value pairs
and hold some information if we install
anything with NPM it'll get put in this
file inside a dependencies object so
let's go ahead and let's clear this up
and do NPM install or I and then no -
sass ok and that's going to install it
what it's gonna do is create a node
modules folder up here anytime you
install something with NPM it gets put
in the node modules now notice we have a
ton of files in here
that's because node SAS itself has its
own dependencies and then some of those
dependencies have dependencies and all
that stuff is in here so you don't have
to worry about this you never have to go
in this folder and touch anything it's
also not going to get deployed to your
server so it just kind of sits there all
right now we have node SAS installed so
the next thing we need to do is set it
up so that it works now to do this we
use something called an NPM script and
you can see we have this scripts object
and it has this test what I'm gonna do
is change this test to SAS I'm just
going to call it SAS we could call it
anything and this is just echoing
something out so I'm gonna just get rid
of this double ampersand exit one and
just change this right here to say hello
from will say hello from SAS script I
guess doesn't matter
and save and now down here to clear the
cell we can do ctrl L and to run it us
an NPM script we do NPM run and then the
name of the script and we called it SAS
so let's do that
and you can see we get hello from SAS
script so obviously this isn't what we
wanted to do I was just giving you an
example of in showing you how to run it
so let's take out everything in between
the double quotes and we want this to
run the node SAS program so node SAS
then we're going to add the dash W flag
which means watch okay so we want to
watch the s CSS folder which we just
created and we want to set an output so
- oh we want to output the compiled SAS
to dist slash CSS like that and then we
just want to add the dash dash recursive
flag so recursive because if we don't do
this we're gonna have some issues with
partials and having it auto reload so
that's it a very simple so just to
reiterate notes ass is gonna watch this
file it's gonna compile all of our sass
into regular CSS and put it in this file
and we don't even have to create the CSS
file in the distal do it on its own so
let's save this and let's go down here
and let's run it so NPM run SAS okay
it's gonna do this it's just gonna kind
of just stop and it's just watching the
s CSS folder so now we'll do is go into
our main file and let's write a little
bit of sass so I'm gonna create a
variable so to create a variable we use
a money sign and we're gonna call this
primary - color use a colon hair to
assign it to let's say number sign four
four four which is a dark gray and then
I'm going to just put in a body tag and
for our in the body I'm going to say
background and let's set that to the
primary color now once I save watch what
happens so we're gonna get a green
message down here saying that it
rendered complete and now if we look in
our disk folder we now have an s CSS
folder if we look in there we have a
main.css so it basically took the sass
file compiled it into regular CSS and
put it here and if we look at that file
this is what's in it just a body with
the background of gray okay now you
don't want to touch this you don't want
to touch your regular CSS file that's
that's the compiled CSS you want to work
within your s CSS okay so that's what
we'll be doing now if we go back to our
project here you'll see there's no gray
background the reason for that is in our
index.html we didn't include any CSS so
what we want to include is the compiled
version so we want to go into CSS and
then main dot CSS so let's put a link
tag here and let's say in CSS slash main
dot CSS and save and now you can see we
have the gray background so whenever we
add anything to our sass it'll auto
update so let's make the color we'll say
color white and save and there we go so
it's gonna just Auto reload so this is a
nice little workflow having node sass
and live server 4 vs code because you
can just update your sass it gets
compiled and then it auto reloads in the
browser alright so what I'm gonna do now
since we have our basically have our
workflow setup is I'm going to open a
new terminal so I want to keep this
running I'm gonna click the plus sign a
new terminal I'm just gonna create a git
repository but before I do that I'm
gonna just create a file called git
ignore dot git ignore so let's say touch
and the touch command just creates a
file so we'll say touch dot git ignore I
spell that right get ignore and you can
see that right here get ignore I'm gonna
just click on that and go inside of it
and just put in node underscore modules
because we don't want that to be added
to our repository that's just our
dependencies so let's go ahead and just
save that file and close it and then
let's initialize a git repository so
we'll say git init and that what that
does is it just creates a hidden folder
called dot git and all of our
repositories
where stuff goes in there so I want to
add everything that we've done so far so
we'll say get add dot so add all and
then let's make a commit to the
repository right now it's just in the
staging area now I do have a get a crash
course on my channel if you want to
watch that if you're interested but
we're just going to do get commit we
want to put a dash M flag so that we can
just put a comment in here and we'll
just say initial I'll say initial
workflow setup like that and then it
gets committed okay we're not going to
push it to github or anything right now
it's just local okay so that's it let's
go back to our other terminal where our
node SAS is running because you want
this to run down here because if you
have an error like let's remove the
money sign and save and you'll see SAS
will actually give us an error and tell
us where it is and what's wrong so let's
put that back all right
okay so I think that that's gonna do it
for this video now that we have
everything set up so in the next video
we're gonna start to add our markup to
our H index HTML and then we'll start to
work on our CSS or we'll create the menu
button and all that stuff so I will see
you in the next video