alright guys so we're going to deploy
this website to github pages so github
pages allows you to basically host any
static site for free can also host react
client-side apps or angular client-side
apps just anything that is that doesn't
have a back-end or a server and it's
free it gives you HTTPS it's it's just a
really cool service so in order to do
this we have to push to a repository
we're also going to install a package
using NPM called gh-pages which gives us
kind of a terminal CLI to deploy our
application so first thing let's create
a repository so in github just go to new
repository I'm gonna call this modern
portfolio and will say responsive
portfolio website let's create it and
I've already done the init I've already
added my stuff and done my commits if
you haven't done that already
then you want to first initialize
actually first of all create a git
ignore a dot get ignore file and add
node modules ok once you do that you can
get an it which will create a repository
a local repository then you want to get
add all ok add dot and then you want to
get about fit get commit dash em and
then just whatever you want say initial
commit or something like that once you
do that you have it in your local
repository now what you want to do is
add github as a remote so if we go back
to that page here it gives us the
command to put in just get remote
command so let's grab that let's go back
and paste that in ok we shouldn't get
any response it's just gonna go to the
next line let's go back again and let's
push so this is the basically the
initial push to the master branch so
let's go back and paste that in and run
it and it should push okay if you don't
have your SSH keys set up go ahead and
do that I have a video that I did about
two weeks ago or so called SSH crash
course and some DevOps
and in that video I show you how to
create SSH keys as well as add them to
github or you can just use HTTP however
you want to get your repository up so if
I reload this page
you now have our repository we can
dismiss this that's not this is nothing
so let's say risk not tolerable whatever
it doesn't matter so now our project is
here now to deploy it we're going to
install something it's called gh-pages
so let's say npm install righ - pages
and then we want to go to our package
JSON file and we want to add here
anywhere in here let's go right below
main and let's add in home page and you
want to put HTTP our HTTP actually and
then your github username so mine is
Brad
Travis II it's not Thomas II can't spell
my own name that's embarrassing so dot
github dot
slash and then the name of the
repository and in my case I said modern
underscore portfolio okay so that's
gonna be my home page now we want to do
is create a deploy script so just like
we have this a script let's go ahead and
put a comma here and let's say deploy so
for deploy we want to run gah - pages
actually this needs to be in quotes so
gah - pages and then we want to add the
D flag and then the directory so - D and
the directory that we want to basically
deploy - that we want to be our website
is the dist folder or the dist directory
okay so we want to put that in there so
let's save this and let's go down here
clear this out and let's run NPM run
deploy and hopefully this works okay so
we get published but we should have got
some other stuff I believe let's just
try it out so we'll go HTTP
ass yeah let's say Brad traversée can I
spell my name right this time
Brad Travis e-dot github dot modern
underscore portfolio and there we go so
our application is now live and let's
just test things out so we have our home
page we have our boat page my work and
how to reach me
cool I'll test the responsiveness l
which should be no different just
because it's remote but we'll just test
it oh good everything is stacked alright
so we have this now deployed to the
internet now if you don't want to use
this domain right here you can go to
your Prada repository and you can go to
settings and go down to where it says
domain our custom domain and you can add
in a domain now obviously you have to
register this domain so what I suggest
for registering domain is Namecheap not
named chap Jesus I cannot spell today so
I bought that guy's so namecheap.com
domains are very cheap so this is where
I register all my domains and if you
follow the instructions whereas it's
right here learn more it's going to show
you how to basically point your domain
to github and then you can use that as
opposed to your github io whatever but
I'm not going to go through that I just
wanted to get it on the Internet
another thing you could do is use manage
hosting I like in-motion hosting com I
actually have a video if you search for
cPanel on YouTube it's like the fifth
fourth or fifth video by traversing
media obviously and we go through we
sign up for an account we hook up a
website we add email accounts we add FTP
all that stuff and I'm going to put a
link in the description for in motion
that actually has my affiliate so if you
guys do decide to go with in motion and
use that affiliate I'd appreciate that
but I have actually have a website with
them a shared home
account under code demos comm as you can
see there's nothing here so if I wanted
to open up an FTP client like filezilla
and connect to it so my host would be
code demos comm and my username is code
demos and password and connect and let's
go into the public HTML that's our web
site root and then all I would have to
do is grab my files
let me grab those real quick so if we go
to let's see where is it I'm just trying
to find the project that we just created
where the hell is it
let me just search for it real quick and
you guys can't see this it's off screen
let's see Modern Portfolio alright here
it is
so this is our project and again the
dist folder is what you want to upload
so everything in the disk for let's just
go ahead and let's grab everything in
here and let's drag it over and
shouldn't take long at all so you can
see right here things that are getting
uploaded and it should now be uploaded
so I'm gonna go back over here and
reload and there we go so now we have
code demos uploaded to in motion so you
have a lot of a lot of ways to deploy
especially a static website it's very
very very simple net Liffe is another
good choice there's a lot of them out
there and there's a lot of managed
hosting like hostgator but i like in
motion it's cheap you can see 6:39 for a
business account including you and you
know an email server stuff like that I
believe they include a domain as well
looks like they're giving free SSL's now
I wasn't aware of that so unlimited disk
space and so on so I will put a link if
you if you're interested in in motion
and then again github pages is
completely free but we do have two
deployments now so you can see it's
pretty easy and I think that's gonna be
it guys that's it for this this little
series I hope you liked it I know some
things may not have been clear
especially if you're just getting into
sass I know there was a couple little
times where I could have explained
things a little better and I apologize
for that it happens but hopefully
overall you like the series if you did
please leave it a like and thanks for
watching guys